Hey, AP, the Spanish-
American War
after the sinking of the
American
warship
Maine and the publication of
Delome's letter.  The war
ended with the
Treaty of Paris,
giving the United States
Puerto Rico, Guam,
Cuba, and the Philippines,
leading to the
Philippine-
American War.
But Americans
debated
imperialism.  Some
believed that it was necessary
to compete with
Europe, while others
argued that
spreading
American
culture was a
white man's burden.  But
anti-imperialists
believed that
imperialism
contradicted
American
values ​​such as
freedom and equality.
President Theodore
Roosevelt was also an
imperialist.  His "
Implication" from the
Monroe Doctrine to Roosevelt
argued that the United States
had the right to
intervene in
Latin American affairs
to maintain peace and
stability.  His
foreign policy
was called "
big
stick diplomacy," and an example of
this was
Roosevelt's support for the
Panamanian independence movement
to build the
Panama Canal.
Period 7 also
includes the Progressive
Movement, which was a
period of social
activism and
political reform.
Journalists
investigating the chaos
inspired reforms by
exposing social
problems and
political corruption.
Ida Tarbell exposed
Standard Oil, Ida Wells
spoke out against
lynching, and
Upton
Sinclair's film The Jungle
exposed the
meatpacking
industry,
while Jacob Riis
photographed poor
living conditions in cities.
Roosevelt was also the
first progressive
president.  His "
Square Agreement"
promoted
consumer protection, control
of corporations, and
conservation of resources.
He did this by
disbanding trusts
, creating
national parks, and
establishing the
Food and Drug Administration.
Presidents William
Howard Taft and Woodrow
Wilson also
oversaw
progressive reforms,
including the passage of the
16th through 19th Amendments.
Economic reform
was achieved
through the
Clayton Antitrust Act and
the creation of the
Federal
Reserve System.
But the reforms took a back seat
when World War I broke out in
Europe in 1914
.  Although
President Wilson
maintained neutrality
, the country shifted to
war production
to support the
Allied cause.  And
after years of
unrestricted
German submarine
warfare and the publication of the
Zimmermann Telegram
, America entered the
war in 1917.
During the war,
civil liberties
were restricted by the
Espionage and
Sedition Acts, and
federal power
was expanded
through new
organizations such as the
War
Industries Board.
President Wilson
created a plan
to avoid future
conflicts
called the "14 Points,"
which he
hoped would be
added to the
Treaty of Versailles.  But the Senate
refused
to ratify the treaty
, mainly
because of the controversial
League of Nations.
Reservationists
such as Henry Cabot
Lodge opposed
the League of Nations because
they feared it would
interfere with
American
autonomy.  After
World
War I, a period of
prosperity and
social change came, known
as the "
Roaring Twenties."  At
this time, Americans
were buying cars
and new home
appliances.  Women who had
recently gained the
right to vote also
expressed themselves
through their
new
flapper style.  And the mass
exodus of
African Americans from the
Jim
Crow South to the North,
known as the Great
Migration, led to the
Harlem
Renaissance.  It was a
flowering of black
culture through
art, poetry, and
jazz music.  And
young Americans
danced to this
music in clubs and
speakeasies.  These were
secret underground
clubs that served
alcohol since the
passage of the 18th
Amendment, which created the
period known as
Prohibition.  But the
rapid changes of the
1920s were met with a
backlash.
Nativism grew after
the war, leading to
immigration quota laws
and the Red Scare.  And
racial tensions
have sparked several
race riots,
such as the
Tulsa massacre.  And
religious
fundamentalism
opposed the
doctrine of evolution,
as seen in the
Scopes Monkey Trial.  But the
Roaring Twenties
ended with the
stock market crash of
October 1929, which
began the Great
Depression.  The economic
crisis was
caused by
excessive
credit spending, buying
stocks on margin, and a
crisis in
agriculture.
Americans lost
their savings,
jobs, and homes under the
poor leadership of
President Herbert
Hoover, who took no
action.  But
in the 1932 election,
Franklin D. Roosevelt
promised the
American
people relief,
recovery, and
reform through
his "New Deal."
Unemployment assistance
included
programs such as the
Works Progress Administration.  He
also introduced
reforms such as the
Federal
Deposit Insurance Corporation and
Social
Security.  But the
New Deal
was criticized for
overstepping
federal
authority,
especially by the
Supreme Court.
Ultimately, the Great
Depression ended with
the start of
World War II.
Roosevelt tried
to maintain neutrality
, but approved the
"cash-and-
carry" and "Lend-Lease" programs
to provide aid to
Allied troops.  He
also introduced
America's first
peacetime draft.
But the Japanese attack on
Pearl Harbor on December 7,
1941, forced
America to enter the
war.  This also
led to
discrimination against
Japanese Americans
and
the internment of Japanese people
.  As during
World War I, women
worked in
munitions and
aircraft factories, but
could also serve in the
Women's Army
Corps.  Other groups,
such as the
Tuskegee Airmen and the
Navajo Codebreakers
, also played
important roles in
America's victory.
Although the war in Europe
ended with the defeat of
Germany shortly
after D-Day, the war in the
Pacific
continued.
Using
the research and
development of the
Manhattan
Project, President
Harry Truman decided
to use the atomic
bomb to force
the Japanese to surrender.  Thus
, the seventh period
ends with
the end of
World War II and
the creation of the
United Nations, which
has a significant impact on
America's future foreign policy.
Thanks for watching,
and if you want
more
help from APUSH,
such as
tutorials,
timelines, and
short description videos,
be sure
to check out the
best review
package.